Shavuah tov שבוע טוב, Shavuah tov, today's daf דף daf is daf
ayin gimmel דף ע"ג. daf ayin gimmel. We are picking up at
the bottom of ayin bet amud bet ע"ב עמוד ב', ayin bet
amud bet, and so ayin gimmel ע"ג ayin gimmel starts a new
topic but actually the end of ayin bet amud bet ע"ב עמוד
ב' ayin bet amud bet is a very nice flow-in because ayin
bet ע"ב ayin bet was about the haba bemachteret הבא במחתרת, haba
bemachteret, the guy who is coming into a tunnel and that he
was understood to be somebody who was prepared to kill the homeowner
and therefore the homeowner could do an act of self-defense and protect
himself etc. except in exceptional cases where he knew that his life
was not at stake.
But at the same time we pointed out aspects of the Gemara
גמרא Gemara which really seem to highlight the idea that maybe the
Gemara גמרא Gemara is thinking about this not just as an act
of self-defense, obviously self-defense is what allows it, but maybe the actual
act of killing the person is a type of a Beis Din
din בית דין דין. Beis Din din. And we saw it most
recently when the Gemara גמרא Gemara sort of spoke about machtart- you
know his machtarto zo hi hatra'ato מחתרתו זו היא התראתו. machtarto zo
hi hatra'ato. His machteret מחתרת machteret is his warning.
So you could just say that means his machteret מחתרת machteret proves
that he's prepared to use lethal force, which is what Rashi רש"י
Rashi does say. But the use of the word hatra'ah התראה hatra'ah
indicated that it was like a normal court case and the guy
needed warning. And then Rashi רש"י Rashi gave an almost bizarre scenario
of a guy who breaks into your house where Rashi רש"י Rashi
doesn't say if it's clear he's ready to kill you then you
can kill him, I mean obviously would be true, but Rashi רש"י
Rashi describes a case, okay a guy broke into my back door
not through a tunnel so if I give him warning in front
of edim עדים edim and I say you know that if you
do this I'm going to use lethal force and he says yes
I know and even so I'm prepared to do it etc. like
Rashi רש"י Rashi didn't say he has to then go ahead and
do it like toch k- well I guess he's not actually doing
the crime you're preventing the crime but anyway so it made it
sound very much like a classic case of warning in a court
case and so on. So with that in mind we're going to
continue but this whole
idea of the pursuer and intervening and so on is going to
very much be the Mishna משנה Mishna that we're going to begin
when we get to ayin gimmel amud aleph ע"ג עמוד א'. ayin
gimmel amud aleph. So let's take a look here at the bottom
of ayin bet amud bet ע"ב עמוד ב' ayin bet amud bet
where it says like this. It says Amar Rav Huna אמר רב
הונא, Amar Rav Huna, it is 1 2 3 4 5 6
7- about 13 lines from the bottom it starts with the words
hi hatra'ato היא התראתו. hi hatra'ato. Amar Rav Huna אמר רב הונא,
Amar Rav Huna, katan erodef nitan lehatzilo benafsho קטן הרודף ניתן להצילו
בנפשו. katan erodef nitan lehatzilo benafsho. If you have a minor that
is running after somebody to kill them, okay, you can actually save
the potential victim with the life of the minor. Okay and here
it exactly seems on the one hand we're talking about erodef הרודף,
erodef, we're talking about haba bemachteret הבא במחתרת haba bemachteret that's understood
to be a rodef רודף. rodef. Here rodef רודף rodef is like
the guy's actively running after somebody to kill them. And as I
said that's going to very much be the sort of
flow-in and the transition in the next daf דף. daf. But here
it also serves as a very important juxtaposition like it starts responding
to the subtext. You're suggesting here maybe that there's an idea that
you kill the guy who breaks into the house because of a
type of a din דין, din, you used the word hatra'ah התראה
hatra'ah and there was an idea of din דין din going on
here. No I got to tell you even if it's a minor.
It has nothing to do- a minor we would never bring to
a court case. A minor isn't held legally responsible for his actions.
But it's not about judging the perpetrator, it's about saving the potential
victim. And therefore even in a case of a minor you do
what you need to do to save the potential victim. So it
serves as a very good counterpoint to what we just said. Wait
let's just get into it a little bit. Okay so it says
kasavar rodef eino tzarich hatra'ah קסבר רודף אינו צריך התראה kasavar rodef
eino tzarich hatra'ah and that's exactly what the Gemara גמרא Gemara says.
A pursuer doesn't need hatra'ah התראה, hatra'ah, so the tunnel counts as
hatra'ah התראה. hatra'ah.
Fundamentally you don't need hatra'ah התראה hatra'ah if the guy- if there's
a potential victim whose life is at stake,
it's about saving the victim. Lo shena gadol lo shena katan לא
שנא גדול ולא שנא קטן, lo shena gadol lo shena katan, it
doesn't matter an adult or a minor we do what we need
to do to save the victim. Aitivei Rav Chisda leRav Huna איתיביה
רב חסדא לרב הונא, Aitivei Rav Chisda leRav Huna, Rav Chisda asked
Rav Huna. One minute we have the classic Mishna משנה Mishna which
is so important for discussions of abortion, yatza rosho ein nogim bo
יצא ראשו אין נוגעים בו. yatza rosho ein nogim bo. If a
fetus is endangering the mother's life you can actually dismember it or
whatever in the mother's womb in order to protect the mother's life.
That's because at that stage it is considered to be that the
fetus is not yet a full life so obviously the mother's full
life takes precedence over the fetus. However as soon as the head
emerges the fetus is considered to be now a full life so
what entitles you to sacrifice the fetus's life for the mother's? Okay
so ein nogim bo אין נוגעים בו, ein nogim bo, she'ein dochin
nefesh mipnei nefesh שאין דוחים נפש מפני נפש, she'ein dochin nefesh mipnei
nefesh, you don't push off one life for another life. Now of
course it raises interesting a whole wealth of interesting questions or not
only interesting practical questions. Let's say if you did nothing there's a
high chance they would both die, right? So it's not choosing one
over the other you're choosing a life, saving one over losing two.
But you have to be active. It's almost like the classic the
train question they always ask these ethical questions right? A train is
coming. down it's going to kill, you
know, whatever, hundred people are going to die, but if you switch
the switch, you can have it run over one person. Do you
actively act to, you know, and kill one to save a hundred,
or do you nothing and let a hundred die? Anyway, there's also
the question, right, about, you
know, what are they doing with these self-driving cars?
Yeah, yeah, they're having—they're trying to program that in.
Right, oh, that's interesting.
Okay, right, right, right. Independent? Yeah, yeah, yeah. So רש"י Rashi then
also deals with questions, you know, about, like, do you hand over
one person to the enemy if they're asking for one person even
though he's innocent in order to save everybody else? You know, what
do you do if it's one against many? Right? Anyway, but we're
not going to get into all those really important and fascinating questions.
But the point here is why can you not touch the infant
once its head emerges? Right? Why don't you say he's a רודף?
rodef? Like, you just said it has nothing to do with responsibility,
with guilt, with blameability, okay? It's protecting the person who is being
pursued. All right? So why don't
we go ahead and, you know, take the infant's life to save
the mother? The mother's being pursued. So the גמרא Gemara says no.
שאני התם אמאי רודף הוא? Shani hasham amai rodef hu? So it
says שאני התם משמיא קא רדפו. Shani hasham mishmaya ka radfu. There's
a difference, there she's being pursued by heaven. Okay, now what does
that mean she's being pursued by heaven? Well, I—partly what this means
is, okay, so you don't need somebody to be responsible, okay? To
be, like, legally responsible, the pursuer, in order to save the pursued.
Okay, but you might think that they need to have been somewhat
blameworthy, right? There's an—there could be a sense of, sort of, being—having
doing the wrong thing. You're seen as the one who's at fault.
Okay, so we're not holding you legally responsible, but—and this isn't a
דין, din, this isn't a judgment, but in order to protect one
life over the other, we've got to decide that one is innocent
and one is to some degree at fault. Right? So if that's
true, you know, maybe, so if somebody is ten years old, and,
you know, they know what they're doing, so they're not legally liable,
but they're blameworthy in this situation. So that might be an issue.
Okay, but if that were true though, then this would mean that
under a certain age, nobody would ever be considered a רודף. rodef.
Another possibility is no, forget fault. It's not about fault. It's about
the—just the reality of being pursued and being a pursuer. Okay, and
even if nobody's at fault. But there are some questions where you
can't identify who is the pursued and who is the pursuer. Like,
if, for example, you had an infant that was falling off of
a roof, okay, and that was going to, I don't know, hit
in the middle of a raft and cause the raft to sink,
or whatever it might be, even though the infant would have been—would
be totally innocent, right? No—right? But there's still—the innocent is the pursuer,
right? It's coming and through some action it's going to actually injure
and take people's lives, right? So it's innocent, but it's the pursuer,
the physical reality, it's coming down, it's going to hit the boat,
destroy these people. So therefore, you know what, you protect the pursued
over the pursuer even if it has nothing to do with fault.
But in this case, right, like, this is a completely—it's not some—something
falling and about to destroy a raft. It's a completely, the way
רמב"ם Rambam says, it's like a completely natural event, giving birth. Giving
birth encounters complications. And sometimes in the process of giving birth, you
know, and certainly in the past, obviously even today, you know, mothers
would very often die in childbirth in the context of birth. So
what משמיא קא רדפו mishmaya ka radfu might be saying is there's
no pursuer here, you know? There's an infant being born and the
mother's life is—we don't look at the infant as a pursuer even
though you could say the physical fact of the way it's coming
out of the mother, but, you know, it's very different when that's
happening as part of a natural event, right? Than when, you know,
in the physical
reality something out of the ordinary is happening and it's threatening lives
of other people. I mean, look, sadly, you know, they had—there were
all these cases about like in the Holocaust or other cases, right?
That people are all hiding, right? And the Nazis or whoever are
around there, and the baby's about to cry, right? And they suffocate
the baby to protect everybody else, right? So you could say it's
choosing one over many, otherwise would have all died, but it's also—forget
that, you know, let's assume they wouldn't have—you know, whatever, it wasn't
the Nazis, they weren't going to kill the babies, it wasn't a
question of one over many. Nevertheless, the crying of the baby is
seen as the pursuing, right? The endangering of everybody else's lives. So
it's really defining that sense of who's—can you identify the pursuer? And
that seems to be what the גמרא's Gemara answer, משמיא קא רדפו,
mishmaya ka radfu, you can't label the baby in this case a
pursuer. Michal, you wanted to say something.
Isn't this something that is discussed between בן ברית ben berit and
שאינו בן ברית,
she-eino
ben
berit, like is this between—?
Well, yes. Okay, so it'll be implicitly addressed. So let's keep on
going. Okay, נימא מסייע ליה. neimai mesayaye lei.
Let's see if we can support you, now that we've challenged you,
if we can support you, this idea of, you know, it doesn't
matter if the person is blameworthy. רודף, rodef, רודף אחר חברו להורגו,
rodef achar chaveiro lehorgo, somebody
who is running after his friend in order to—not much of a
friend—to kill him. Okay, אמר לו, amar lo, ראה ישראל הוא בן
ברית הוא והתורה אמרה שופך דם האדם באדם דמו ישפך.
Re'eh Yisrael hu ben brit
hu vehaTorah amrah shopech dam ha'adam ba'adam damo yishapech.
So somebody who is seeing this says to the pursuer, "What are
you doing? That guy is a fellow Jew, the Torah says that
if you spill the blood, your blood will be spilled." Obviously, this
sounds like classic התראה, hatra'ah, right? So here we're once again introducing
into the dynamic of רודף rodef and, you know, saving, protecting a
life, almost making it a דין din and introducing a התראה hatra'ah
model. Okay, so you see this guy, you give him this התראה,
hatra'ah, okay, so דם דמו ישפך, dam damo yishapech, אמר תורה הצל
דמו של זה בדמו של זה. amar Torah hatzel damo shel zeh
bedamo shel zeh.
Okay,
did I skip a line? No. Okay, so and the Torah says
that like if I, if I have to choose, I am going
to save his life with your life. So if like in ordinary
you say if you're מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbat, you're going to be
חייב מיתה. chayav mita. So here the warning is, it's אסור assur
in the Torah, and if you do it, you're going to be
liable, your life, in order to protect his life. So it's classically
modeled after התראה, hatra'ah, sounds very much like the דין din model.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is saying, so the very fact that
you need to do this warning makes it sound like a קטן
katan would not be... you couldn't save the life if it was
just a קטן katan running after. It sounds like it has this
element of דין, din, not just this element of protecting the one
who's being run after. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הא היא
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה היא, ha hi Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda hi,
that is following רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda. Why?
דתניא רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר חבר אין צריך התראה לפי שלא
ניתנה התראה אלא להבחין בין שוגג למזיד. de-tanya Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda
omer chaver ein tzarich hatra'ah lefi shelo nitnah hatra'ah ela le-havchin bein
shogeg le-mezid. That somebody who is a חבר, chaver, okay, somebody who,
you know, is like a knowledgeable...
I don't want to say תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, but you know,
whatever, very knowledgeable of Torah and so on, you don't have to
warn them because the warning is only because the purpose of the
warning is not a formal requirement for warning somebody, we're not talking
about רודף, rodef, let's say מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbat, there's not a
formal requirement, the only purpose is to know that the person is
intentional or not intentional. And therefore if you anyway know that the
person is intentional, therefore you're going to be... you can execute him
anyway. Now what does that have to do with us? Let me
just double check רש"י, Rashi, make sure I'm saying this right.
Oh, okay, I thought I made a mistake, one minute.
Oh, okay, so actually רש"י Rashi reads it... I was trying to
make things work a different way, but I actually had misread it
a minute ago. I read the previous thing that the very fact
that you have to warn him was showing that it... there is
an element of blame and whatever and it wouldn't apply to a
קטן. katan. רש"י Rashi actually explains that the גמרא Gemara is actually
understanding the other way. The fact that, because, oh, it's actually the
גמרא Gemara says נימא מסייע ליה, nima messayei lei, this is actually
supporting the idea that you could kill a קטן. katan. So how
does this whole, sorry, apologize, I misread it, how does the whole
idea that you're warning him and saying, "Don't do this, the Torah
says it, etc."? How does that support the idea that you can
do, that you can, you know, take the life of a קטן
katan who's a רודף? rodef? So רש"י Rashi says because you never
have in that, in that description, you never have the pursuer saying
back, "Yes, I know it's forbidden to me for do this and
even so I'm going to do it." So since you don't have
קבלת התראה, kabbalat hatra'ah, it sounds like you don't have to apply
the דין din model and you don't have the person to have
to be really liable and really sort of, you know, transgressing knowingly.
So then the גמרא Gemara responds back and says no, the reason
you didn't need קבלת התראה kabbalat hatra'ah was because it was רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda, and רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda sort of drops the formal התראה hatra'ah requirements.
It's enough that the guy's informed. So once you said what you
said, even though the guy didn't say יודע אני ואף על פי
כן, yode'a ani ve'af al pi ken, etc., nevertheless for him you
don't need all of that. You just need the guy to know
what he's doing and you need the guy to be informed. So
that's why the fact that you don't need a קבלת התראה kabbalat
hatra'ah is not a proof that you would say the same thing
by a minor. But I have to tell you, I mean because
my misreading was because I don't really... don't really understand this. If
this is not a principle of דין din and this is a
principle of protecting the נרדף, nirdat, and this would apply to a
minor, to a two-day-old infant or a one-day-old infant, right? So why
are we describing it with the התראה hatra'ah altogether? Why do they
give the case that you say any of this? You don't have
to say any of this. The time it takes you to say
this, you could be using to try to intervene and to save
this other guy's life. You know, so that's what I'm not... I'm
not understanding. Right? It seems that the גמרא Gemara is really holding
up this contrast. There's a דין din model and then there's a
just save the pursuer, the נפקא מינה nafka mina is the case
of the קטן katan that presents a perfect נפקא מינה. nafka mina.
Okay, so this case here, it's true there's no קבלת התראה, kabbalat
hatra'ah, but who needed the whole warning to begin with? So I'm
not exactly sure why that scene is a support for the non-דין
din model of what's going on here. Yes?
One point about what it says in the earlier
קטן הרודף ניתן להצילו. katan harodef nittan lehatzilo.
No, no. We'll discuss it when we get to the משנה Mishnah.
*mishnah*, but the נרדף nirdaf *nerdaf*, we're trying to save the נרדף
nirdaf *nerdaf*. Yes, yes, yes. להציל את הנרדף בנפשו *l'hatzil et hanerdaf
b'nafsho* of the רודף rodef *rodef*, of the קטן katan, *katan*. Right,
but I'll get to your read in a minute. Okay. Anyway, so
that's a little strange. גמרא Gemara, *gemara* says fine, you know, maybe
you do maybe it is a case of דין din *din*, but
you just don't need קבלת התראה hatra'ah, *kabbalat hatra'ah* because it's רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה *Rabbi Yose b'rabbi Yehuda*. But again just to repeat
myself, if it's not a case of דין din *din*, then I
have no idea why they're bothering with the whole התראה hasra'ah, *hatra'ah*.
Anyway, let's keep on going. Okay, תא שמע *ta shema*, come and
hear. רודף rodef שהיה רודף rodef, אחר חבירו להורגו *rodef shehayah rodef
achar chaveiro l'horgo*. אמר לו *amar lo*, once again, ראה שישראל הוא
ובן ברית הוא והתורה אמרה שופך דם האדם באדם דמו ישפך *re'eh
sheyisrael hu u'ven brit hu v'hatorah amrah shofech dam ha'adam ba'adam damo
yishapech*. אם אמר יודע אני שהוא כן *im amar yode'a ani shehu
ken*, yes I'm aware and nevertheless I'm pursuing him with this in
mind, פטור *patur*. Okay, excuse me, יודע אני שהוא כן פטור *yode'a
ani shehu ken patur*. Oh, if he just says I know, but
he doesn't say I'm doing it accepting the responsibility for that, then
he's exempt. על מנת כן אני עושה *al m'nat ken ani oseh*,
I'm doing it with accepting that knowledge and responsibility, חייב *chayav*. So
that's of course again bizarre. So you have a guy who's pursuing,
he's about to murder somebody, if he doesn't do the right type
of קבלת התראה *kabbalat hatra'ah*, you can't protect the, you know, the
innocent victim? Right, that's completely bizarre. Okay, so anyway but the גמרא
Gemara, *gemara* says, ah, you see it's a דין din *din* case,
and therefore obviously would only apply to a גדול *gadol*. So the
גמרא Gemara. *gemara* says, no, לא צריכא דקאי בתרי עברי דנהרא דלא
מצי אצולי *lo tzricha d'ka'i bitrei evrei d'nahara d'lo matzi atzulei*. No,
no, no, no, you misunderstood the case. This is not a case
of saving the נרדף nirdaf. *nerdaf*. You can't save the נרדף nirdaf.
*nerdaf*. It's happening on the other bank of the river, and you're
just at most you'll be able to do is bring this guy
to a בית דין beis din? *beit din* afterwards, and you're trying
to warn him in order to bring him to a בית דין
beis din *beit din*, but you cannot do anything to intervene. You're
on the other bank of the river. Okay, מאי קא בעי *mai
ka ba'ei*, what is it that you might be able to do?
אתויי לבי דינא *atuyei l'vei dina*, to bring him to a בית
דין beis din *beit din* afterwards. בי דינא בעי התראה *bei dina
ba'ei hatra'ah*, so for that you're going to need to do התראה
*hatra'ah*. Okay, so therefore you don't have to obviously, but it's not
really about needing to do a התראה *hatra'ah* in order to protect
the נרדף *nerdaf*. איבעית אימא *iba'it eima*, if you want you could
say, אמר לך רב הונא אנא דאמרי כתנא דמחתרת דאמר מחתרתו זו
zo היא התראתו *amar lach Rav Huna ana d'amri k'tanna d'machteret d'amar
machterto zu hi hatra'ato*. Actually, no, I could be saying,
I that says by the קטן katan. *katan* that's רודף rodef *rodef*
that you take the life of the קטן *katan*, right, I could
be saying like that idea by the מחתרת machteret *machteret* in the
case of the מחתרת *machteret* you don't need התראה *hatra'ah* because the
מחתרת *machteret* is the התראה *hatra'ah*. Now, when you say the מחתרת
*machteret* is the התראה *hatra'ah* is very different than saying you don't
need התראה *hatra'ah*. המחתרת זו היא התראתו *hamachteret zu hi hatra'ato* says
in principle you need התראה *hatra'ah*, but somehow the מחתרת *machteret* counts
for it. Okay, what רב הונא *Rav Huna* is doing is he's
saying, no, no, no, מחתרתו זו היא התראתו *machterto zu hi hatra'ato*
means fundamentally you don't need התראה *hatra'ah* in a case of רודף
rodef, *rodef*. It's not about the guy being guilty. It's about protecting
the innocent party. Right, if you look at רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*, זו
היא התראתו *zu hi hatra'ato*, אלמא משום דמחזיקינן ליה רודף rodeif. לא
בעי התראה *almah mishum d'machzikinan lei rodef lo ba'ei hatra'ah*. Once you
know the guy is threatening the life of the other person, it's
not it's as if you have התראה *hatra'ah*, forget התראה *hatra'ah*, it's
not about התראה *hatra'ah*. It's about protecting the victim and it would
apply even to a קטן *katan*. So this סוגיא *sugya* here at
the end really distills two different models of רודף rodeif, *rodef*. The
one that of
course intuitively we would sort of agree with is all about protecting
the victim, or the other right, sure, protecting the victim is what
gives you license, but you still have to do it as a
type of דין din *din*. Okay, now it's one thing to say
automatically it's a type of דין din, *din*, it's another thing to
start imposing these requirements that you have to give a formal warning,
you have to receive the warning, like how the heck are you
going to save the guy's life when you're going through this process?
Just one more point. But again to say that the נפקא מינה
*nafka mina* focusing not on דין din *din* but completely on the
נרדף *nerdaf* leads to the idea that even a minor, okay, and
of course by the minor you're why don't you say, well, one
life and the other life, it's not the minor's fault, right, like
the baby who's about to cry, right, if it's not the baby's
fault, so so רב הונא *Rav Huna*'s going one step further. He's
not just saying it's not a case of דין din *din*. He's
saying you don't even need blameworthiness. It's just the reality that one
person is engendering,
endangering another person's life and it's possible to label the pursuit and
the pursuer. Sometimes you can't label it. Everybody's endangering everybody else's life
or whatever it is, but if you can label this is the
pursuer and this is the pursued, you protect the pursued over the
pursuer. Yes, again, you had a question.
Yeah, and isn't there shouldn't there
be an aspect of like needing to clarify the situation, right?
Is that is that Well, yes, you but but it's not the
way the language sounds. ישראל הוא ובן ברית הוא והתורה אמרה *Yisrael
hu u'ven brit hu v'hatorah amrah*, right, so the way to read
מחתרתו זו היא התראתו *machterto zu hi hatra'ato* is not to is
the way it's being read at the end is not just to
say you need התראה *hatra'ah* but this counts as התראה *hatra'ah*. It's
saying you need the evidence that the guy is about to use
lethal force or that you know enough to say that it's possible
and therefore so right, you need to clarify, but that's not the
same as creating this התראה *hatra'ah* model. Yes.
Is this a warning on a rabbinic level?
No, well, it's a rabbinic reading of the biblical verses, but it's
under understood as a biblical requirement.
And the ספורנו is saying he doesn't agree with that principle.
No, he totally agrees with it when it comes to executing somebody
in court. It's just completely irrelevant when it comes to saving somebody's
life who's being pursued.
Yeah, no discussion about the Jewish vs. non-Jewish?
Well, yes, it does say ישראל בן ברית הוא, Yisrael ben brit
hu, right? So the implication would be that well, look, you know,
that gets into all those uncomfortable things about that, you know, if
a Jew kills a non-Jew it's not a capital crime or it's
not punishable in court. You know, so it's not punishable in court
by execution. Okay, so then the question would be, it seems from
this גמרא, Gemara you know, that if you had a case of
a רודף rodeif. and a נרדף and the נרדף was a non-Jew
and the רודף was a Jew, it wouldn't be ניתן להצילו בנפשו.
nitan lehatzilo benafsho. That is the subtext of this גמרא, Gemara you
know. That is correct, you picked up on that subtext. Yes, okay.
Alright, but maybe what you could say though is all of those
are going within the דין din model. Actually, that just occurred to
me. Within the דין din model where you need the התראה, so
there, it's only executed by the court in a case of when
a Jew killing a Jew. Okay, but in within the רודף נרדף
rodef nirdaf model and protecting the victim, maybe you could suggest otherwise.
You know what I'm saying, Michal, that maybe the בן ברית ben
brit is דווקא davka within the דין din model. Okay, but anyway,
but that is yes the subtext of that גמרא. Gemara Let's turn
to the next משנה. Mishnah Okay, and now we continue with this
idea of רודף,
and here we completely seem to abandon, seem to abandon the דין
model and it's about protecting the victim, but let's take a look.
Okay, ואלו הן, Ve'elu hen, I shouldn't have said that, but okay,
cause anyway, ואלו הן Ve'elu hen we'll see, שמצילין אותן בנפשן. shematzilin
otan benafshan. The following people you can save, you know, the victims
with the lives of the, I'm going to read it as the
victims with the lives of the pursuers. הרודף אחר חבירו להרגו, Harodef
achar chaveiro lehargo, which is implicit by the whole מחתרת case, right,
which is the phrase we used before, somebody pursuing somebody going to
kill them, you protect the victim. ואחר הזכר ואחר הנערה המאורסה, ve'achar
hazachar ve'achar hana'arah hame'orasah, or running after a man running after another
man to rape him or running after a betrothed maiden.
And the גמרא's Gemara going to extend that to all cases essentially
of rape in a context of מיתת בית דין. mitat beit din.
It's going to be an interesting combination. Okay, rape itself is not
enough, right, we could sort of say, you know, when the גמרא
Gemara says כי כאשר יקום איש על רעהו ורצחו נפש כן הדבר
הזה, ki ka'asher yakum ish al re'ehu uretzacho nefesh ken hadavar hazeh,
it says by the by the נערה המאורסה na'arah hame'orasah who has
been basically raped, so part of what the תורה Torah is doing
is saying, אין לנערה חטא מות, ein lana'arah chet mavet, that you
can't blame her. Right, we know obviously, you know, there were societies
even still today that blame the rape victim and so on. She's
blameless, she's like a murder victim. But what it also could be
saying is that, you know, the act of rape is maybe kind
of somewhat tantamount to murder. There's actually a חזון איש Chazon Ish
that says something like that. So you could have said, you know,
you can stop a rape by the use of lethal force. Okay,
but that is not what the גמרא Gemara is saying. The גמרא
Gemara never like focuses on rape as a crime, you know, obviously
there's punishment, you know, there's whatever, you know, it's like a normal
case of attacking somebody physically. I should say that, an act of
rape is, you know, the תורה Torah has, you pay all these
various fines, he has to marry the girl, etc., but the גמרא
Gemara puts it in the same context of like physical assault. Okay,
not worse, but also not better than, okay, physical, that's how the
גמרא Gemara. sees rape. Okay, but nevertheless, okay, that is not sufficient
here to intervene like in a case of, it would be an
interesting case. Imagine a case of physical assault, somebody's running after somebody
to break their legs. Okay, could you kill them and use lethal
force? I don't even know what the what the law is in,
you know, in secular law, right? I mean obviously if a person
thinks that their life is at risk it's different, right? But anyway,
what would be the law if they were going to do a
terrible act of physical assault but not kill the person? Okay, but
so it is that is not sufficient.
Remember the subway, I forget his name, that that guy in the
subway years ago and he shot at these guys who were.
Yeah, but that probably the claim was he thought his life was
at risk. Let's say it was a case where that wasn't the
claim. I didn't think my life was at risk, but I thought
they were going to break both of my legs, you know, so
I, so you know, so I don't know the answer. Anyway, rape
itself is not enough to intervene with with lethal force. It's the
combination of that with the idea that the act is an עבירה
aveirah that you're חייב מיתה chayav mitah for. Okay, so if it's
the case of זכר zachar or if it's the case of a
betrothed maiden or actually we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara
any married woman or any case of even a חיוב כרת, chiyuv
karet, like any other relatives that you're חייב כרת chayav karet for,
okay, that you can intervene with taking the life. But if it
was, if both parties were consensual, you can't, then it's just somebody's
doing an עבירה, aveirah, and if it's a rape without the חיוב
מיתה, chayav mitah, without the חיוב כרת chiyuv karet you also can't.
So it's a very interesting combination and I would say, because I
said a minute ago, oh, this is not about דין, it's all
about protecting, it's all about the victim, but the fact that you
need it to also be a חיוב מיתה chayav mitah might be
a little bit about, might be suggesting the idea that no, we
need an element of דין here. We need it to be an
act that's seen as an act that were it being done, you
know, again, I don't care about minor adult or whatever. But an
act that is a type of a case that is punishable by
death. And if that's the type of act that's being done, then
we kill the person to save the
נרדף. So there's like a interesting mix of the דין and the
saving of the נרדף. You might not need התראה, you might be
able to do it with a קטן, even if the רודף is
a קטן. It's not an actual, but nevertheless, if we're taking somebody's
life, we have to see that what's being done, being perpetrated is
a capital offense. If what's being perpetrated is not a capital offense,
then we can't protect this person's life. Obviously, I mean, we can't
protect the victim, we will always protect the person's life, that's the
רודף, because then always what's happening is a capital offense. But in
case of a victim of sexual assault, right, then we need it
to be a case where it's sort of seen as a capital
offense together with protecting the potential victim of sexual assault. Yes.
But can you also see that the fact that it's a capital
offense is a measurement of the severity of the act, so outside
the בית דין?
beis din Right, but not the act of,
but that doesn't reflect the protection of the victim, meaning because it's
a,
if it's a case about yes,
adultery is a worse act than intercourse with an unmarried woman, right?
But like how does the,
what you're trying to say is the fact that it's such a
weighty thing means that there's more, somehow it translates into some aspect
of protecting of the victim.
It gives you a greater right to use lethal force to protect
the victim because we've defined that particular act...
Well, that's I think what I meant when I said that it
has to be a capital offense. Oh, you mean you don't need
necessarily the דין idea. You don't need the דין model. You just
need to say like it's such a... But it's still an interesting
combination of you're doing a terrible thing and I'm protecting the victim.
If I was just protecting the victim and what you were doing
wasn't so terrible, then I wouldn't have that license. Right, it's true.
You could talk about the severity of the act without introducing a
quasi בית דין beis din model. But it's not, but it's either
way it's not just about protecting the victim, it doesn't seem to
be. It seems to me you need something else when you are
not dealing with murder. Yes. When, yes.
Can you just clarify, you can still protect the victim, you just
can't do it with lethal force?
Of course, right, of course.
Would you be able to break...
Yes, so there you go, that's a really good question. Right, I
was asking if somebody's limbs were at stake, could you kill the
guy? Let's say somebody's,
it's a case of protecting a victim which you can't use lethal
force for, let's say a rape of an unmarried woman,
etc., can you use non-lethal force? Can you actually... so there it
seems that the answer actually is yes,
but there's a whole case in the גמרא Gemara in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma about the ראש Rosh talking about beating up the guy
who was going to... and certainly presumably if what's being done is
as I said, if rape is perceived of as physical assault, right,
then it certainly seems that you could equally use physical assault and
so on, but...
You'd probably have to at least have a court case where you're
determining whether they're...
Right, and that actually is a case in בבא קמא Bava Kamma
where two guys beat one another up and the question is like
who started it and what, if you started it then I have
a right to use force and to beat you up to stop
you from continuing to beat me. So yes, so but that's also
a very good question. Okay, אבל רודף
אחר בהמה, aval rodef achar behemah, somebody who is pursuing an animal
to have intercourse with
it. So, that's a sexual act, etc., but there's no victim to
protect. Okay, we don't consider the animal a victim that needs to
be protected, all right, it's a human victim. Okay, ומחלל את השבת,
umichalel es ha-Shabbos, or somebody who's going to do a terrible thing
but also victimless, מחלל את השבת, michalel es ha-Shabbos, okay, ועובד עבודת
כוכבים, v'oveid avodah kochavim, or עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
also terrible sin but no victim, אין מצילים אותו בנפשו, ein matzilin
oso b'nafsho, you don't save them. Now, you don't intervene with lethal
force. So again, what the משנה Mishnah is very clear, it's a
very nice beautiful clear משנה Mishnah is you need it to be
a terrible sin with a victim. Okay, if there's a terrible sin
and no victim, no. If there's a victim and no terrible sin,
okay,
like rape of a single woman or whatever, also no. You need
some combination of the two. Now I want to say something about
the phrase מצילים אותו בנפשו matzilin oso b'nafsho because the simple means
is you save the victim
with the life of the perpetrator, okay, but what does that mean
in the case of a מחלל שבת? m'chalel Shabbos? You don't save
who with their life? Who's being saved? So it could just be
borrowing the phrase. Obviously there's nobody to be saved here, that's the
whole point, there's no victim. Okay, but if you look at רש"י,
Rashi רש"י Rashi says אלו שמצילין אותן מן העבירה בנפשן, eilu she-matzilin
osan min ha-aveirah b'nafshan, ניתן להורגן לכל אדם כדי להצילן מן העבירה.
nitan l'horgan l'chol adam k'dei l'hatzilan
min ha-aveirah. So because of this weird combination of victim and serious
offense, רש"י Rashi actually says who are
you saving? You're saving the potential perpetrator from sinning. Okay, now of
course that's bizarre. If I can use lethal force to save your...
from sinning, okay, it's better you should die than you should do
this terrible עבירה, aveira, right, then why shouldn't I be able to
do it even if it's victimless, even if you're about to מחלל
שבת? mechallel Shabbos? Okay, so maybe I don't know somehow I need
the victim to allow me to intervene but fundamentally what I'm doing
is I'm saving you from sinning. So that's רש״י's Rashi bothered because
of the grammar of מצילין אותן בנפשן. matzilin osan benafshan. So it's
like I'm saving you with your own soul. Okay, תוספות Tosafos points
out that you know תוספות Tosafos also goes back and forth about
this because there's other cases where it's clear like he talks about
it's like when it talks about running after a woman it says
מצילין אותן בנפשו, matzilin osan benafsho, right, when it talks about you
know or אותה בנפשו. otah benafsho. So it's clear that the the
one you're saving is the victim not the perpetrator. Okay, so this
whole question of how to read this phrase gets into the inherent
ambiguity between the the fact that you have these two criteria. You
need it to be a victim and you need it to be
a serious offense. So what's it about? Is it about the offense
or is it about the victim? And all that plays out in
how you interpret the phrase מצילין אותן בנפשן. matzilin osan benafshan. Do
people get that sort of how that's all encapsulated in that question
of how to read that phrase? Okay, let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: מניין לרודף אחר חבירו להרגו?
minayin l'rodeif achar chaveiro l'horgo? How do you know somebody running after
somebody to kill him שניתן להצילו בנפשו, shenitan l'hatzilo benafsho, that you
can actually save him with the you know you can protect the
I'm going to just read it that way protect the victim with
the life of the pursuer? תלמוד לומר: לא תעמוד על דם רעך,
talmud lomar lo ta'amod al dam rei'echa. do not stand idly by.
Now that doesn't tell you you have license to use lethal force
but anyway the גמרא Gemara says והא להכי הוא דאתא? v'ha l'hachi
hu d'ata? Is that what it teaches you? המיבעי ליה לכדתניא, hamiba'ei
lei l'chidetanya, we need it for the following thing: מניין לרואה את
חבירו שהוא טובע בנהר או חיה גוררתו או ליסטים באין עליו שהוא
חייב להצילו? minayin l'ro'eh es chaveiro shehu tovei'a banahar o chayah gorarto
o listim ba'in alav shehu chayav l'hatzilo? We need it's not telling
you use of lethal force, it's telling you the obligation to save
somebody's life. You see somebody's life in danger, how do you know
you have an obligation to to help the guy? תלמוד לומר Talmud
lomar: the verse says: לא תעמוד על דם רעך. lo ta'amod al
dam re'echa, Okay, so it's telling you the basic obligation, it's not
telling you you can use lethal force. אין הכי נמי, In hachi
nami, you're right. אלא ניתן להצילו בנפשו מנלן? ella nitan l'hatzilo benafsho
minalan? So where do you know you can use lethal force? אתיא
בקל וחומר מנערה המאורסה. atya b'kal vachomer minara hame'urasa. It's a קל
וחומר kal vachomer from the case of the betrothed maiden. By the
betrothed maiden it says: אין מושיע לה, ein moshia lah, nobody was
able to save her, which suggests that if somebody was able to
intervene and save, he would do it at whatever cost that came
to. And if that's true by the maiden by the betrothed maiden,
it's also going to be true by a potential murder victim. Let's
take a look. Okay, אתיא בקל וחומר מנערה המאורסה. atya b'kal vachomer
minara hame'urasa. מה נערה המאורסה שלא באה אלא לפגמה, mah nara hame'urasa
shelo ba'ah ella l'fogmah, he's not going to come to kill her,
he's only going to come to I don't know how you translate
לפגמה, l'fogmah, to how do they translate it there? To blemish her?
There's got to be a stronger word than blemish. But anyway, to
what? Defile her maybe is a whatever anyway, spoil her. Okay, so
we'll get to what that word means in a minute, but he's
obviously coming to inflict some offense on her but not to actually
kill her. And nevertheless, אמרה תורה, amra Torah, the Torah says: ניתן
להצילה בנפשו. nitan l'hatzilah benafsho. Get the grammar there? So clearly the
one you're saving is not the perpetrator, it's the victim. You can
save her with the life of the perpetrator. Okay, so that's what
you learn from נערה המאורסה nara hame'urasa because it says אין מושיע
לה, ein moshia lah, so implicitly you could if you could have
saved you would have saved her, even with the life of the
perpetrator. If that's true when the victim is not it's not a
life, so רודף אחר חבירו להרגו על אחת כמה וכמה. rodeif achar
chaveiro l'horgo al achas kama v'chama. How much more so should you
be able to intervene and use lethal force? So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, וכי עונשין מן הדין? v'chi onshin min hadin? Can
you punish somebody based on a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? Now again,
that phrase עונשין מן הדין onshin min hadin is a בית דין
beis din discussion. Can we impose a בית דין beis din penalty
based on we can't impose a בית דין Beis Din penalty based
on a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. It's once again evoking a בית
דין model. Here I'm not punishing the perpetrator, I'm saving the victim.
Okay, so it's interesting again, the use of that גמרא's Gemara phrase
again indicates a little bit of the בית דין idea in the
background. But no, I'm sorry, you can't make that type of a
connection even if it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay, so דבי
רבי תנא: devei Rebbe tana: Fine, it's not the קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, היקשה הוא. hekesha hu. The verse explicitly connects the two ideas.
כי כאשר יקום איש על רעהו ורצחו נפש, ki ka'asher yakum ish
al re'ehu uritzacho nafesh, as a person would rise up against his
friend so is this matter. So as I said, the simple פשט
pshat of that is the woman is blameless. But what it's doing
is it's comparing the case of rape to a case of murder.
So the גמרא Gemara says וכי מה למדנו מרוצח מעתה? v'chi mah
lamadnu merotzei'ach mei'atah? What is murder telling us and informing us about
the case of rape? It already said the woman was victimless was
blameless. So הרי זה בא ללמד ונמצא למד. harei zeh ba l'lamed
v'nimtza lamed. It's coming as if it's coming to teach us. רוצח
Rotzei'ach is going to inform you about something about this case about
the נערה המאורסה. nara hame'urasa. But in the end, actually it comes
to teach but it winds up learning. That's a great phrase to
use in other context. I came to teach but I left anyway
but it winds up learning. What did it what did we learn?
What did it learn? מקיש רוצח ונערה מאורסה. makish rotzeach vena'arah me'orasah.
נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah becomes the teacher. מה נערה מאורסה ניתן להציל
בנפשו, mah na'arah me'orasah nitan lehatzil b'nafsho, the same way you can-
you save the woman with the life of the perpetrator by נערה
מאורסה, na'arah me'orasah, אף רוצח ניתן להציל בנפשו, af rotzeach nitan lehatzil
b'nafsho, even the case of the murder victim you can- of the
potential murder victim, you can save him with the life of the
pursuer. ונערה מאורסה גופא מנלן, vena'arah me'orasah gufah minalan, and where do
you know that that's true by
נערה מאורסה? na'arah me'orasah? כדתני דבי רבי ישמאל, k'detana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael,
like דבי רבי ישמאל d'bei Rabbi Yishmael teaches. תני דבי רבי ישמאל,
tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, רבי ישמאל Rabbi Yishmael teaches, ואין מושיע לה.
v'ein moshia lah. There is none to save her. היש מושיע לה,
ha yesh moshia lah, if there was anybody available to save her,
בכל דבר שיכול להושיע, b'chol davar sheyachol lehoshiya, you would save her
with whatever means possible. Did you have a question, Janna? Good. Okay,
גופא. gufa. Now let's go back for a moment to look at
the obligation to save a life, even when there is no, what
do you call it, even when there is no- even- even without
the use of lethal force, just the basic obligation. So גופא. gufa.
מנלן לרואה חבירו שטובע בנהר וחיה גוררתו או לסטים באין עליו שחייב
להצילו? minalan l'ro'eh chaveiro shetoveia b'nahar v'chaya gorereto o listim ba'in alav
shechayiv lehatzilo? How do you know if somebody is being attacked or
potentially by- by animals, by bandits, that you should try to save
the person? You have an obligation to save the person? תלמוד לומר
Talmud lomar לא תעמוד על דם רעך. lo ta'amod al dam re'echa.
Don't stand idly by. So מהכא דהכא נפקא? me'hasha d'hacha nafka? Is
that the basis for it? מהתם נפקא. me'hatam nafka. We learn it
from the following. אבידת גופו מנלן? aveidat gufo minalan? We know you
have to return somebody's lost objects. How do you know that you
have to protect somebody's life? Okay, it's what it refers to as
אבידת גופו. aveidat gufo. It's obviously their life isn't already lost, okay,
but you could say, you know, the object also isn't like completely
lost to them. It's in the middle of the street. It's at-
it's in danger of being completely lost to them but could be
restored. So somebody's life is at risk, is endangered of being lost
to the person, but you can restore it. How do you know
that you have to restore it? תלמוד לומר והשבתו לו. talmud lomar
vahasheivoto lo. This is by the מצוה mitzvah to return a lost
object. You should return it to him. But it's a play on
words, והשבתו לו. vahasheivoto lo. You should return a person to himself.
You should help a person save their- you know, protect their own
life. You should protect the person's life. So this is very important.
So אם מהתם, im me'hatam, now, if so, just from that, הוה
אמינא, hava amina, I would have thought, הני מילי בנפשיה. hanei mili
b'nafshei. Yes, you have to use your effort, personal efforts to save
somebody- to return some- you know, to protect somebody's life, the same
way you use your personal efforts to return a lost object. אבל
מטרח ומיגר אגורי, aval mitrach u'meigar agurei,
but, you know, if it really means a lot of effort, not
just, you know, doing something immediate, but I can't do it myself,
I have to go spend the money, I have to hire people,
somebody is drowning, I have to go take some money and like
hire a boat to go out to take him or whatever, so
I might think that that far you don't have to go. אימא
לא, eima lo,
maybe you're not obligated to that extent. קמשמע לן kama mashma lan
that you are. That לא תעמוד על דם רעך lo ta'amod al
dam rei'echa says not just like- it's not just any מצוה. mitzvah.
It's not like- you know, normally a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh doesn't
push you for more action. The עשה aseh pushes you for more.
But what this is saying is, had it just been an עשה,
aseh, you would have said, okay, like any other עשה, aseh, I
do it if it's possible. I don't have to do it if
it's like not- if it requires a certain- a certain demand of,
you know, me putting myself out or whatever. I mean, depends on
the עשה aseh or whatnot. But anyway, לא תעמוד על דם רעך
lo ta'amod al dam rei'echa is telling you, no, no, no, this
is extremely weighty. If you're just standing idly by, if you're not
doing everything you can do, then you're- then you're- then you're not
fulfilling your obligation. You have to really exert all efforts to save
him. Now, of course, this gets back to the question David raised,
because you notice the גמרא Gemara says you have to spend money,
you have to whatever, right? It doesn't say you have to risk
your life. It doesn't even say you have to risk your limb,
right? How far do you have to go? You know, sometimes somebody
jumps after somebody to save a drowning person, and they wind up
drowning, right? So that is an important question. From the way the
גמרא Gemara frames it, it does not sound like it would extend
as far as actually risking your life, okay, but it's an important
question how far that goes. Anyway, and also in general, you know,
we always talk about פיקוח נפש דוחה שבת, pikuach nefesh docheh Shabbat,
where is that מצוה mitzvah of פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh? Right? So
פשט p'shat that's here. That's the מצוה mitzvah of והשבתו לו vahasheivoto
lo and לא תעמוד על דם רעך, lo ta'amod al dam rei'echa,
you know, seems to be the core of the מצוה mitzvah of
פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. Okay, so that's the obligation to save, but
what we're then dealing with is then the obligation not only to
save but actually to use lethal force in doing that. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara, says like this.
Okay, קמשמע לן. kama mashma lan. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Our rabbis
taught. אחד הרודף אחר חבירו להורגו ואחר הזכר ואחר הנערה מאורסה ואחר
חייבי מיתות בית דין ואחר חייבי כריתות. echad haraudef achar chaveiro l'horgo
v'achar hazachar v'achar hana'arah me'orasah v'achar chayivei mitot beit din v'achar chayivei
keritot. So this expands the case of the murder victim. You have
the case of the raping a man or raping a woman who's
betrothed, and then really any type of forbidden sexual act in the
case where the person is being forced on them. Okay, so that
would be a case of a married woman, it would be a
case of, you know, it doesn't have to actually be a death
penalty, even כרת. karet. So you know, sister, brother's wife, or whatever.
Any of those cases of the עריות, arayot, okay, then that combination
of the severity of the act and the victim means you intervene
with lethal force.
Where were we?
אבל aval אנסה לכהן גדול גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט, anesa l'kohen gadol
grusha v'chalutza l'kohen hedyot, but if it's a violation but a more
minor violation in terms of not from the perspective of the victim,
but from the perspective of God, from the perspective of the עבירה,
aveira, okay, it's a case
of a כהן גדול kohen gadol is going to rape a גרושה
grusha or,
I'm sorry, a כהן kohen is going to go rape a גרושה
grusha or a כהן גדול kohen gadol is going to rape an
אלמנה almana or something of that sort. סיפא לאו אין מצילן אותה
בנפשו, seifa lav ein matzilun otah b'nafsho, you would not intervene with
the use of lethal force. Okay? Again, what could you intervene with
any force? That we had that discussion. Why wouldn't you save her?
Because it's רודף. It's רודף, meaning the person is being pursued, right?
If it's not people are engaging in a sin. The גמרא Gemara
will be explicit about it later, but the point here is it's
רודף. Okay, and okay, so then the גמרא Gemara says,
נסתחפה
בעבירה אין מצילן אותה בנפשו. nistafa ba'aveira ein matzilun otah b'nafsho. If
she has already engaged in a sin or, it's not blaming her,
and an act has already been done to her, then she can
no longer be saved. Now here becomes, you know, I have to
be honest, I've been using the phrase rape because I think it
resonates with
our contemporary mores
about rape. But in the גמרא, Gemara it is true that she
is that it's a case of she's she's not willing. Like if
she's a willing participant this doesn't apply, because then nothing is being
done to her, she's willingly doing it to herself, whatever, you know,
she's a participant. But it doesn't mean that the גמרא Gemara is
highlighting the fact that it's rape is the problem. She can't be
willing because then she's not a victim. But if she's a the
point is that she's a victim, okay, but nevertheless part of the
problem here for the גמרא Gemara is not just an act of
sex being forced upon her. Part of the victim is that word
before that we had before, פגמא. pegama. She's being spoiled. Okay? Which
basically means that I was having I was talking to דבורה Devora
about this the other night and saying like, I don't get it
exactly because the גמרא Gemara like like it doesn't mean that she
goes from being a virgin to a non-virgin because it applies even
to a married woman. Okay, so but what it means is she's
being spoiled. דבורה Devora put it beautifully. She said, the גמרא Gemara
sees that every woman belongs to a man, either either the man
she's currently married to or the man she will be married to.
So therefore if the act if the woman is married and has
had intercourse with her husband, she hasn't been spoiled, right? Even though
she's no longer a virgin, right? But somebody comes and rapes her,
then he's spoiling her. It's that other man who is having sex
with her who is now spoiling her. So if she's a single
woman, even though in theory she could marry anybody, but nevertheless we
don't we don't sort of see the perpetrator as the future husband,
so he is now spoiling her, right, to that next to the
man. That's the פגמא. pegama. Okay? But therefore because that's the model,
if she has already had intercourse, even if she's not to blame,
with a man that isn't her husband, one man already raped her.
Okay? I mean, it's horrific, right? One man already raped her. The
next guy is not spoiling her. She's already spoiled goods. Do you
hear the point? So if it was נסתחפה בה... nistafa ba... I
mean, it's it's very difficult to think about, but that's the גמרא's
Gemara point. If it was נסתחפה בה, nistafa ba, part of the
reason you use lethal force is because this man is spoiling her,
is being פוגם pogeim her. Okay? And therefore if she's already נסתחפה
nistafa even to no fault of her own, she's already spoiled goods,
then you can't use lethal force to protect her. You seem troubled
there, Johnny, because you're not understanding us because you're troubled by this.
Yeah, absolutely.
Like I see that from רש״י, Rashi, I just like when I
when we first read it, I was thinking like, meaning you come
into the situation too late, like the act's already been done.
Right, you can't kill him then
after the fact. Right, and not like I
wasn't reading it as like, okay if two years later...
Yeah, we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara. that that's later
that I mean you're right, maybe there would be other ways to
have read this phrase. It's going to seem like it's pretty inescapable
based on how the גמרא Gemara reads it, okay? And the גמרא
Gemara really emphasizes, as we're about to get to, the idea of
פגם. pegam. So it's not the idea of rape, it's it's what
that rape does, it's how that rape is פוגם pogaim the person.
Okay? And therefore if the person's already נסתחפה, nistafa, then it's not.
So it's very interesting. Now, that could still be that we see
it as a type of a protection, but what we're protecting the
woman from is not the sort of, you know, the violent act
of rape, what we're protecting the woman from is is from being
נסתחפה, nistafa, and that's what we're protecting the woman. So it's a
very different mindset that you have to get your head around, okay?
But it's I do still think it's very much victim-oriented, but from
a different perspective than our... contemporary one. Okay, נערה בשדה, na'arah basadeh,
אין מצילין אותה בנפשו, ein matzilim otah b'nafsho, יש לה מושיע, yesh
la moshia,
if somebody could have saved her without the use of lethal force,
that presumably is what it means, אין מצילין אותה בנפשו, ein matzilim
otah b'nafsho, then you can't take the guy's life because then use
the non-lethal ways. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda אומר omer אף af אומרת
omeret הניחו לו hanichu lo שלא shelo יהרגני. yehergeni. The woman says,
"Don't intervene, if you try to intervene, I'm afraid he's going to
kill me," okay, so you would think okay, that's, you know, she's
saying that because she's afraid for her life, but if we can
still intervene we're going to intervene if we can save her life
and save her from being raped, but he says no, once she
says that, you cannot, you cannot kill the guy anymore. Okay, that's
also disturbing and we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara Okay,
מנא הני מילי? mena hani mili? Where does all this come from?
אמר קרא, amar kra, ולנערה לא תעשה דבר. v'lana'arah lo ta'aseh davar.
Do not do anything to her. אין לנערה חטא מות. ein lana'arah
chet mavet. She is not deserving of death. Now נערה na'arah is
written without a ה. heh. So נער, na'ar, זה zeh זכר. zachar.
So even if we're talking not about a betrothed woman, about a
man being run after to be raped. Okay, נערה, na'arah, זו נערה
המאורסה. na'arah hame'orasah.
That's the case of the betrothed maiden. חטא, chet, אלו elu חייבי
כריתות. chayvei kritot.
Other things that are considered a weighty sin, like כרת, karet, like
case of a sister, for example. מות, mavet, זה zeh אלו elu
חייבי מיתות בית דין, chayvei mitot beit din,
even weightier sin. So it's not just those two cases, any עריות
arayot that fits into this category. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, okay, כולהו למה לי? kulhu lamah li? Why did I
need all those phrases? Why couldn't I have just extrapolated? צריכי, tzrichi,
you need it. דאי כתב רחמנא de'i katav rachamana נער na'ar
without the ה, heh, משום דלאו אורחיה, mishum delav orchei, because it
then just told us about the, about the case of the man
being raped, משום דלאו אורחיה, mishum delav orchei,
because for a man, you know, for a man to be penetrated
by another man is not, is not as normal. So therefore, and
therefore the idea of the rape there might be seen as, you
know, more horrific and needs more protecting than the case of a
woman being raped.
ואי כתב רחמנא ve'i katav rachamana נערה, na'arah, משום דקא פגים לה.
mishum deka pagim lah.
There's the פגים, pagim, right? If it said נערה, na'arah, that's because
that act of rape is spoiling her. אבל נער דלא קא פגים
ליה. aval na'ar delo ka pagim leh. So here's a man that's
been raped, and we just said that that is less natural and
more horrific, you know, for the man from his experience of it.
But even though it might be more horrific in terms of the
experience, it's not פוגם pogem him. So again, the פוגם pogem is
being used in a very specific way of the woman becoming spoiled
goods, as it were. Okay, אימא לא, eima lo, so maybe you're
not entitled to intervene by the man. So I had to say
both. ואי כתב רחמנא הני, ve'i katav rachamana hanei, if it had
just said those two, משום דהאי לאו אורחיה הוא והאי קא פגים
לה. mishum dehai lav orchei hu vehai ka pagim lah. Each one
has something very weighty. Okay, the man it's unnatural and the woman
it is פוגם pogem her. אבל שאר עריות, aval she'ar arayot, others,
where it's a case let's say, so here רש״י Rashi says like
a case of let's say a married woman who's already had intercourse,
okay, דאורחייהו, de'orchaihu, first of all because it's a woman that act
is not seen as unnatural, ולא נפיש פגמייהו, v'lo nafish pigmaihu,
and yes there's a פגם, pgam, it is some other man having
intercourse with them, but they're not going from being a betrothed virgin,
you know like רש״י Rashi says like that's like the most precious
goods, as it were. You know, she's already loved by her husband
and she's still a virgin, and that be like there the sense
of פגם pgam is at the highest. So other cases where it's
not at that high, so אימא לא, eima lo, maybe you're not
entitled to intervene, כתב רחמנא חטא, ketav rachamana chet, to include it
even to other cases of sexual sin, even where presumably there is
פגם, pgam, but not the same degree of פגם. pgam. Nevertheless. ואי
כתב רחמנא חטא, ve'i katav rachamana chet, הוי אמינא אפילו חייבי לאוין.
havai amina afilu chayvei lavin.
If it had just said a sin, I would have said okay,
even simple negative prohibitions like a כהן kohen and a גרושה. grushah.
כתב רחמנא מות. ketav rachamana mavet.
No, it has to be a weighty sin, either כרת karet or
death penalty. ואי כתב רחמנא מות, ve'i katav rachamana mavet, if it
had said that, הוי אמינא חייבי מיתות בית דין אין חייבי כריתות
לא. havai amina chayvei mitot beit din in chayvei kritot lo. It
couldn't have just said מות, mavet, I would have limited it to
the cases of the death penalty. So כתב רחמנא חטא, ketav rachamana
chet, so therefore it said חטא. chet. The balance between the two
is we get חייבי מיתה chayvei mitah and חייבי כרת, chayvei karet,
weighty sexual sins. Okay, fine. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
וליכתוב רחמנא חטא מות v'lichtov rachamana chet mavet ולא בעי נער נערה?
v'lo ba'ei na'ar na'arah? So why not just say חטא מות? chet
mavet? That includes all cases of weighty sexual sins and you don't
have to explicitly include the case of the man or the case
of a נערה המאורסה. na'arah hame'orasah. גמרא Gemara says you know what,
אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, you're right. Once it says חטא
ומות, chet u'mavet, we don't need נער ונערה na'ar v'na'arah to tell
me the scope of what type of sexual victims we're talking about.
So ואלא נער ונערה, ve'ela na'ar v'na'arah, so what function do those
have? חד למעוטי עובד עבודת כוכבים וחד למעוטי בהמה ושבת. chad l'me'uti
oved avodat kochavim v'chad l'me'uti behemah v'shabbat.
So one is to exclude, those are to highlight for me that
it's not just about the sin, that it's about the fact that
there's a victim here. If it had just said חטא מות, chet
mavet, I would have said great, I'll use lethal force to stop
anybody from doing a serious עבירה. aveirah. I'll go out there and
I'll kill all the people who are about to be מחלל שבת.
mechallel shabbat. By the way, I should probably check that. תוספות Tosafos
has a great question. You see somebody about to be מחלל שבת.
mechallel Shabbos. He says, "What's the הווא אמינא? hava amina? I see
somebody about to be מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbos, so I see them
on שבת. Shabbos. I'm going to use lethal force to stop them?
So I'm going to be מחלל שבת." mechallel Shabbos.
Anyway, so you can go look at the תוספות, Tosafos, that's a
cute question. Anyway, so maybe if I just had חטא מות, chet
moves, I would have said it's all about the עבירה, aveira, it's
not about the victim. So I would have included עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, weighty עבירות aveiras I have to intervene. So it says no,
נערה. na'arah. Then what do I need the other one for? Fine,
it's about a victim of a sexual assault. Maybe that's—or it's about
a sexual thing. So maybe I should even include it to a
case of a בהמה, behemah, an animal that's about to be, you
know, have an act of intercourse done to it. So therefore the
other word tells me, no, it's not sexual sin versus non-sexual sin.
It's about victim as opposed to a non-victim. So the נער na'ar
and נערה na'arah is telling me it's not just to stop terrible
sins from being done, okay, and the other one is telling me
it's not just about sexual sins, it's about a terrible sin with
a victim of a sexual sin. Okay, and therefore it doesn't include
בהמה behemah and it doesn't include שבת Shabbos and עבודה זרה avodah
zarah and so on. Okay, so very nice clear defining, it's that
interesting hybrid of those two. חד למיעוטי עבודה זרה—oh chad le-mi'utei avodah
zarah wait a minute, let's go. חד למיעוטי עבודה זרה, chad le-mi'utei
avodah zarah, it's not just about sin, וחד למיעוטי בהמה. ve-chad le-mi'utei
behemah. רש"י Rashi says once you exclude עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you
obviously exclude שבת, Shabbos, so it's really חד למיעוטי בהמה. chad le-mi'utei
behemah. That it's not just about the weightiness of the sins, and
it's not just about sexual sin, it's about a sexual sin with
a victim. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Where
am I?
בהמה. behemah. I lost my place.
בהמה, behemah, שבת, Shabbos, okay. I'm sorry, we just have to hold
you Micha because I want to get a little further. Okay, ורבי
שמעון בן יוחאי דאמר עובד עבודה זרה ניתן להצילו בנפשו. ve-Rebbi Shimon
ben Yochai de-amar oved avodah zarah nitzan le-hatzilo be-nafsho. Ah, this is
very interesting. There are actually some תנאים Tanna'im that actually thought that
it was all about the sin, and it wasn't about the victim.
רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rebbi Shimon ben Yochai says, you see somebody
about to be עובד עבודה זרה, oved avodah zarah, you can use
lethal force. Now that might be עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, I mean,
we know the גמרא has, you know, wiping out all the עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, the גמרא is very harsh about עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. But nevertheless, he does say it doesn't necessarily require a victim.
At least there are some sins where you would use lethal force
like עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So למה לי? lama li? So then
what am I going to do with the נער na'ar and נערה?
na'arah? What am I excluding? Fine, חד למיעוטי בהמה, chad le-mi'utei behemah,
well one still has to exclude the case of בהמה, behemah, okay,
that's not, you know, it still doesn't get to the level. וחד
למיעוטי שבת. ve-chad le-mi'utei Shabbos. Now one to exclude שבת, Shabbos, because
I would have thought, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, דהקיש שבת
מחילה-חילה לעבודה זרה. de-keish Shabbos me-chila-chila le-avodah zarah. If you can actually
use lethal force to stop עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, maybe we should
use lethal force to stop שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so here we have
רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rebbi Shimon bar Yochai is not saying any
serious עבירה, aveira, but the most serious עבירה aveira doesn't need a
victim. Yes, normally you need a victim, and בהמה behemah wouldn't be
included. But I am going to say from this we could also
learn out that when we're dealing with the most serious of עבירות,
aveiras, like עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, then forget the idea of a
victim, then you סתם stam use lethal force. Okay, now we have
another interesting position. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rebbi Elazar bar Rebbi Shimon.
Now רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rebbi Elazar bar Rebbi Shimon, who is
the son, he takes it one step further than his father.
דאמר מחלל שבת ניתן להצילו בנפשו. de-amar mechallel Shabbos nitzan le-hatzilo be-nafsho.
Heck, let's just keep on going with this approach. If you can
use lethal force to stop עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you can use
it to stop שבת. Shabbos. Seriousness of the sin does it. דאיתקיש
שבת שבת מחילה-חילה לעבודה זרה. de-isha Shabbos Shabbos me-chila-chila le-avodah zarah. Now
not every terrible sin, just שבת Shabbos which is equal to עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, okay, because it uses the same word of desecrating.
Okay, so then what do you do with the פסוקים? pesukim? So
what are the פסוקים pesukim excluding? מאי איכא למימר? mai ika le-meimar?
חד למיעוטי בהמה. chad le-mi'utei behemah. So we still have to exclude
בהמה. behemah. If it's either it's the weightiest of sins, שבת Shabbos
or עבודה זרה avodah zarah even without a victim, or it is
sexual sins with a victim, and then you exclude בהמה. behemah. Okay,
so what do you need the other thing to exclude? דאידך, de-idach,
we really not, don't need it to exclude. אתי דאתיא מנער כתב
נמי נערה. ati de-asya mi-na'ar katav nami na'arah. The נער na'ar and
נערה, na'arah, we're not going to make any big deal about. Okay,
but what we find out from here is that in our משנה
it's the combination of weighty sin plus a victim. We also clarified
that the victim is not just a victim of rape, it's a
victim of being נפגם, nifgam, of being defiled, okay, which limits it
to certain types of cases. And there are some תנאים Tanna'im that
say some cases, it's just about saving the person from the עבירה,
aveira, עבודה זרה avodah zarah and שבת. Shabbos. Now even there I
would ask, are we saving the person or are we protecting the
community? Right, I think you could frame שבת Shabbos and עבודה זרה
avodah zarah as a victim. If עבודה זרה avodah zarah is being
done in the community, the community's religious identity is being—not intervened with,
it's being—not tolerated, but you know what I mean, not stood up
against, the community's religious identity is being endangered, and the same by
חילול שבת. chillul Shabbos. I think there's a way to frame those
as about being a victim as well. Okay,
I don't know what to say because in terms of time, can
you guys give me like six more minutes or
whatever to
just— I'm just gonna do it though. Okay. Make sure to watch
it though. It's really important. Okay.
We gotta catch up a little bit. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר אף
אומר הניחה לו שלא יהרגנה. Rabbi Yehuda Omer af omer hinicha lo
shelo yehergena. So this is a case where the woman says, "No,
no, no, don't kill him, you know, don't intervene, I'm afraid he's
going to kill me." Now why should that change things? Her life
is still at risk, she's saying that because she's afraid for her
life or whatever, she's still at risk of being raped. So why
should that change things? So let's take a look. במאי קמיפלגי, Bemai
kamifligi, what's the debate about? So the גמרא says, אמר רבא במקפדת
על פגמה, Amar Rava bemakpedet al pigma, she's still obviously is concerned
about her פגמה, pigma, she doesn't want to be raped obviously. I
mean, when she's saying leave him alone, it's not because she's okay
with being raped, she doesn't want that, והניחה שלא יהרגנה, v'hiniha shelo
yehergena, but she's still
saying don't, don't do this cause I'm not prepared to give up,
I don't want to lose my, I don't want him to kill
me. I don't want to get raped, but I don't want him
to kill me. Okay, so רבנן סברי אפגמה קפיד רחמנא, Rabanan savri
apigma kapid Rachmana, the תורה Torah cares about her being נפגם, nifgam,
is protecting her from
פגם, pegam, והרי מקפדת אפגמה, v'harei makpedet apigma, as opposed to a
person who's consensual, we're not gonna come and protect, you have to
be a victim, we're not going to protect somebody who's willingly allowing
themselves to be נפגם, nifgam, okay, but you're not willing, you're afraid
for your life or whatever, you're still a victim, you don't want
to be נפגם, nifgam, we're going to protect it. Okay, and we're
going to intervene. All right, ורבי יהודה, v'Rabbi Yehuda, and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda would say no.
האי דקאמר רחמנא קטליה, Hai d'ka'amar Rachmana katlei, the reason the תורה
Torah says kill the guy is not because just to protect her
from this פגם pegam or from being raped, but משום דמסרה נפשה
לקטלא, mishum d'masra nafsha l'ktala, because there'll be a case where a
woman is going to be raped and she would actually give up
her life to save herself from being raped. Now, you need two
circumstances: A, you need a woman who's willing, who's more important to
give up their life than to be raped. Now, not everybody would
feel that way. רש"י says צנועות tznuot will be prepared to give
up their lives rather than be raped. You know, it raises the
interesting question of יהרג ואל יעבור, yehareg v'al ya'avor, which we'll get
to tomorrow, right? Does יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg v'al ya'avor apply to
a, a man isn't supposed to do a sexual sin rather let
himself be killed, do we say the same thing about a woman?
Okay, that'll be an interesting discussion tomorrow. So number one, you need
the woman to want, to be prepared to give up her life.
But the other thing is, whether she's halachically obligated or not. But
the other thing is, she needs to have the choice. Most of
the time, she doesn't have a choice. If the guy wants to
rape her, he'll rape her, right, even if she says kill me
instead, right, he's not going to listen to her. So, right, I'm
serious, right? So, so therefore, but nevertheless, what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is saying here is, I think the reason the תורה Torah said
intervene was not to protect her from being raped. I think the
reason the תורה Torah said intervene was because sometimes her life will
be at stake. There will be times where she will give up
her life, she will be in a position to sacrifice her life
rather than being raped, and because her life is at stake, that's
why you intervene. Okay? So it's a very different framing of it.
רבי יהודה האי דקאמר רחמנא קטליה משום דמסרה נפשה לקטלא, Rabbi Yehuda
hai d'ka'amar Rachmana katlei mishum d'masra nafsha l'ktala, she will sometimes give
up her life, and her life is at risk, so that's why.
הא לא מסרה נפשה לקטלא, Ha lo masra nafsha l'ktala, and here
she's saying don't intervene, I don't want him to kill me, so
she is saying, I will, I will not give up my life,
I am not... So, oh, okay, then your life isn't at risk,
we're not going to intervene. So for him, we're only intervening because
we think your life is at risk. As soon as you make
it clear to us you're not giving up your life, we're stepping
back. All right? So אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, amar lei Rav
Pappa l'Abaye, so רב פפא Rav Pappa said to אביי, Abaye, אלמנה
לכהן גדול נמי קא פגים לה, almana l'Kohen Gadol nami ka pagim
lah, so I don't get it. Now if it's all about פגם
pegam and not about life being at risk, cause maybe he thought
until now there was that element, you're telling me even when she
says I'm not giving up my life, it's all about פגם. pegam.
So אלמנה לכהן גדול, almana l'Kohen Gadol, she's also being נפגם. nifgam.
So why don't we also protect, protect her? So אמר ליה פגימה
רבה קפיד רחמנא פגימה זוטא לא קפיד רחמנא, amar lei pgima raba
kapid Rachmana pgima zuta lo kapid Rachmana, only on a big פגימה,
pgima, not on a small פגימה, pgima, which by the way, you
know, going back to, to point made before, might be saying that
the severity of the עבירה, aveira, why is this not a big
פגימה? pgima? Why is אלמנה לכהן גדול almana l'Kohen Gadol not a
big פגימה? pgima? Presumably because it's not a big עבירה. aveira. So
that seems to be reshaping it, that it's not the, you did
such a terrible עבירה, aveira, it's bringing in a בית דין model,
right, or as Gloria wanted to say, it's making it a more
serious offense. No, the bigger the עבירה, aveira, the bigger the פגם.
pegam. An אלמנה almana that's been raped by a כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, yes, she's no longer a virgin, she's נפגם nifgam to her
future husband, she's maybe like a חללה chalalah or whatever it is,
but because the עבירה aveira was not a serious עבירה, aveira, it
somehow leads us to think of the פגם pegam as being a
less serious פגם. pegam. So it's a very interesting observation. But anyway,
but again we have a couple of models here, right? You just
do it because of a big עבירה, aveira, שבת Shabbos or עבודה
זרה, Avoda Zara, but there maybe there's a victim, maybe the community
is the victim, or you know, or the basic point here that
it's about the victim, but it's not just the victim, it's the
victim plus the weightiness of the עבירה. aveira. Is the weightiness of
the עבירה aveira bringing in a דין model? Is the weightiness of
the עבירה aveira bringing in a, you know, just a severity of
the act? Is it increasing the sense of פגם? pegam? Right? Interesting
ways of thinking about that. And finally you have, you know, רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position, which is that it's really not about protecting
the woman from rape, it's about seeing every case of a rape
as a potential case that her life is at risk. And it's
about protecting her life. And when that's not a concern, you would
not intervene. Okay. So that was a pretty big דף. daf. We
will end with that.